ladies and gentlemen the wait is finally
over we're going to finish our epic
series here on endurance fatigue
conditioning whatever the heck you want
to call it this is where we're really
gonna dive into the different aspects of
physiological pieces that make up
conditioning or endurance or the causing
now if you're new to this video or
you've just stumbled upon this a friend
has shared it with you or you've caught
it on YouTube somehow I would encourage
you to take a quick step back go check
out the previous videos there's some in
the five-minute version and some of the
55 version first thing I'd like to step
with start with is number one where I
talk about my definition of endurance
that's gonna be important for later on
this video when we talk about the
physiology of different aspects of
endurance that way you know what the
hell I'm talking about you're on the
same page with nomenclature etc also I'm
not going to cover programming in this
particular video I've done that in a
separate longer video all right so if
you want to know the best exercises to
select for maximizing aerobic
performance or you want to know the
optimal rep range for anaerobic capacity
I've already done that separately you
can have to go check those videos out
okay once you've done that then I would
encourage you to go on to step number
two which is the 55 minute video where I
talk about what I call how we make
cellular energy for exercise now that's
a that's a dumb down or coaching
friendly version of saying metabolism
bioenergetics it is where I go into how
you use fat for fuel versus carbohydrate
what are the pros and cons how how you
use in it from the cells perspective
fuel from the liver versus the blood
versus the muscle itself what practical
implications does that have to why you
get tired during certain events and
others so once you do that now you're
really going to understand this
particular video a lot more or a lot
better because we're gonna take all that
stuff and we're to build directly on it
so a lot of pieces in this video might
not make sense if you skip particularly
that metabolism video or the previous
one but having said that here what we're
going to do is springboard off those
first three pieces and go into why you
actually physiologically get tired and
remember if you've had X biz before or
you have maybe X 5 or 6 years ago or
something or you least maybe you're
coaching but you
gone back and read some textbooks I
don't cover this topic like the textbook
I'm not just going to teach you about
well there's phosphoryl creating a
system aerobic system and I take a more
systematic whole body approach to that
so what I want to understand is why
fatigue is happening this is not just
because of ATP pcr system or glycolysis
alright or gluconeogenesis or whatever
happened to be glycol any of Genesis
that matter all right so it's a bigger
picture that we're also going to jump
into vo2 max specifically I've teased
about this before people use this term a
lot you've heard it but you may not know
exactly what it is and what role that
plays in endurance training and
performance and then finally why you
breathe now this is interesting because
you might be thinking well I breathe
though I own die yes I'll grant you that
but why you might be also thinking well
so I can get oxygen in sure obviously
but why does that actually kill you
what's the actual problem there I don't
think most people really understand that
so that's what I want to get into at the
end and especially because I would say
this active breathing field is probably
the biggest most cutting-edge stuff
happening in all of you in performance
so I want to talk a little research
we've done in our laboratory the studies
we've produced as well as some other
resources you can go learn more about
the breathing stuff for performance so
having said that real quick before we
jump in I want to make sure they're all
in the same page I've been getting a lot
more people jumping on to these videos
recently and I want to take a quick
second to let you know why do these to
begin with there are several reasons why
I created this website a handful of
years ago in a while I'll continue to do
this with these videos well one of the
main reasons is because of probably you
right now so I know a big chunk of you
watching this are in my class one of my
many classes and so what happened was I
would notice specifically or you know
very much so during these metabolism
videos the xvid stuff in those lectures
those are always the hardest for
students and I just started thinking why
is it that the hardest lectures we give
students don't have any opportunity to
take it at their own pace some some
people just had X phase last semester
and got an A well they don't need to sit
through four or five days of really slow
pass some of you took it five or six
years ago maybe you're coming back to
school or you really struggled with
or this piece was really difficult for
you wasn't explained well they went too
fast why is it that everyone gets it at
the same exact pace it didn't make any
sense to me so some students who run up
after class so they'd want a videotape
or they want to record the lectures and
some one extra notes I'm just thinking
this is insane in 2019 why don't I just
take the glaciers put it all up there
and students can take it up their own
pace use the exact same lectures I give
the same PowerPoint you can watch it as
slow as you want as fast as you want you
could watch it at 1.8 speed and get
through it a little quicker for a quick
review you can go back stop it wait What
did he say again I kind of dozed off i
spaced off there or I didn't get that
part at all I'm going to go back to that
quick section this just made a lot more
sense to me in addition when I realize
that I started thinking man there's
probably a lot of people out there that
are coaching that are trainers that are
just super in the field maybe doing
their own workouts that would love the
notice information too but in order to
get it they'd have to get into a
university this is kind of toss the cost
of ton of money they got to take two or
three years of prereqs and then I
thought that's just all garbage and so
what I've done is put this together in a
platform that says you know what
hopefully you know my friends in class
it's helping and hopefully that you're
being able to study and learn at your
own pace this is increasing retention
and the data I've collected has shown
that people are doing much better on
that exams and those either aren't in my
class well you get to benefit from that
but in order to make this thing work the
only viable way to make this thing
happen is to put some sort of crowd
funding behind it so what I actually do
is I have a patreon account that
hopefully will flash up here on the
screen sometimes and you can see where
that is and you can head over to that
make a small donation and what that
really does is support this for my
students this is what allows me to make
these videos I can send them off to Ryan
Ryan is doing a fantastic job producing
them if you've been a fan of these for a
long time you'll notice the production
value is going up exponentially and
that's because I can afford to give Ryan
some money here and there and some other
folks so the quality has gone up I've
actually have some real big surprises
coming soon and in terms of notes and
quiz questions and things like that that
are becoming and that's because people
have been contributing some money so if
you're a student of mine don't even
attempt under no circumstances make a
contribution is you've already paid
enough but if you're not and you're one
of the people out there that are
benefitting benefiting from these videos
and hundreds of our
was a free content ma'am if you could
spare five ten bucks that only goes to
my to my students that I can pay not my
students in this class my graduate
students that I can pay to do other
stuff for me to free it my time to make
these videos so really the money you're
giving me is buying me time or it's
buying me the ability to pay Ryan or
somebody else to help out so enough of
that being said appreciate this support
if you don't have any of that stuff no
worries no problem help share it around
because there's probably lots other
people that would love to see these
videos and don't know they exist
especially people that maybe you're
changing careers I can't afford to go
back to school they're willing to put in
the work they're willing to put the time
they just want good quality information
the more you share it the more those
eyeballs see it and the more the world
improves our training and nutrition and
programming quality so that being said
let's actually finally dive into the
physiology of endurance okay quick quick
backstory here as I mentioned I like to
think about endurance or fatigue
management as going okay you know what
let's think about the entire human body
go through all the physiology and
exercise physiology class instead of
going system by system let's just think
well what are the components step one to
step flat and 20 or 200 whatever Atmos V
I think one of the possible all the
things that have to go right for me to
do human movement so that I can perform
well and then what are all the possible
ways each one of these could be
susceptible to fatigue or could cause
fatigue and so that's what I really am
going to do in this video you'll notice
there are six layers now keep in mind
all six this is going to come in at the
end in fact kids in my class you're
going to need to know these six very
specifically and so what I want to do is
go through each level and talk about
what their basic role in performance is
and then how they get fatigued and then
what you can do about that
quick reminder though sorry he does
quick reminders were eventually going to
get their last little piece here go back
and watch this individual video where I
talk about in detail the different types
of endurance training but very quickly
muscular endurance to me is something
like you know a push-ups in a minute
fifty thirty reps very local to the
muscle itself is not really like a true
metabolic a cardiovascular fatigue it's
a very muscular local issue
inside of that I go high-intensity
endurance think of that as like 30 on 30
off or intervals and then we'll talk
about long duration endurance now in the
other videos I split these up into
further subcategories but for now the
way I'm gonna approach this physiology
section is to think of these three
really distinct paradigms so long
steady-state short high-intensity really
hard intervals and then maybe like
muscular endurance alright now again in
reality I actually in my head and with
my athletes I split them up into a lot
more subcategories but this is the first
level I want to get to you my challenge
to you right now as you're going through
this video if you're thinking well I
don't do anything that's in you know
only one of these three categories great
neither do I so as I'm going through
this material start thinking okay well
you know what he's talking about what
happens if you did like 30 on 30 off but
how would this apply if I'm did
something more like my soccer athletes
or how would this be different for my
hockey players how would this be
different for my personal training
clients so yes I'll acknowledge there
are other training windows within that
and you should be thinking about how
this would change will be different how
this would go up this go down that's
really what should be going on your head
instead of just blanket memorizing oh
there's three types of endurance no
horseshit that's not at all what there
are there are many many many many ones
alright so think about that on your own
I can't do all the thinking for you so
why do we actually get tired as finally
we're gonna get to remember from the
previous video it's really two things
either run out of energy ATP or you
compiled too much waste and sometimes
compiling too much waste stops you from
making more ATP sometimes not sometimes
this is separate but this is really what
we're getting after and in previous
videos I walked you through a giant
slide like this where I took me through
all the different macronutrients how
those get in your stomach what those
doing the blood and where they're stored
and then eventually we walked in through
in painstaking detail basically Olivette
ab ilysm we went through oxidative
phosphorylation and glycolysis we went
through beta oxidation and int G's and
how we use short chain fatty acids along
chain fatty acids for fuel and all these
different things and so you should have
a basic understanding I'm gonna assume
you have this for more the short videos
I think this particular slide was in a
very quick five-minute video
right but having said that we got to
move on now so it's time to actually
jump into these six different layers so
starting off with layer number one in
order to have any kind of human movement
has to start with a neurological system
could be central nervous system could be
peripheral for sure could be combination
point is nerves have to tell muscles
what to do and if we understand the
metabolism going on to nerves we
understand this is primarily driven by
carbohydrate metabolism so the nerves is
least in terms of what I'm aware of I
can't use fat for a fuel source very
efficiently so if you run low on
carbohydrates at the level of the
nervous system we're gonna have a
neurological fatigue now that's a whole
separate issue the whole idea of central
nervous system fatigue with exercise is
pretty overblown poorly understood
peripheral is the bigger issue
nonetheless carbohydrates are your thing
there that doesn't mean you have to be
on a high carbohydrate diet or you'll
have neurological failure that's not at
all what I'm saying I am saying that the
nerves are going to preferentially use
carbohydrate for fuel though now if you
remember from exercise fist class if you
didn't have it or forgot you have to go
back on this on the on but the way that
we have interaction with an action
potential is you have sodium coming in
through one side of the cell and
potassium going for the other one well
in order to get that that gradient reset
we have to use the sodium pump the na+
pump to reset that well that itself
requires ATP I know you cover that next
phase that pump itself because you have
to do something in an active process you
have to reset a gradient it's kind of
like if you were to to launch catapult
well then overclock it back you have to
put energy back on the system to wreak
rank it so that you can hit one flip in
it flies right well that takes ATP to
put it back on the system and so that
fatigue that itself can get become
fatigued the nerves also have a problem
with pH so if it becomes too acidic or
it becomes too basic in the case of
exercise I said acidity is going to be
the problem because it's going to be
functioning on enzymes like everything
else a low pH or high acid well cause
the nerves to be compromised in terms of
performance so moving past the level of
the nerve we've talked in depth already
about the level of
muscle we know that it uses
phosphocreatine glycogen glucose to some
level and fat but the nerve the muscle
itself only stores glycogen right we
store the glucose somewhere else right
we're you know we're you know right so
the muscle only stores PC our glycogen
and fat in terms of fatigue then you can
certainly run out of fossil creatine
that's a big problem that'll be an issue
for certain types of activities muscle
glycogen you're not going to necessarily
get to zero but you can become extremely
depleted to where the muscles start
sending out signals to stop metabolism
fat stores in the muscle otherwise known
as int jeez it's a little bit tricky to
understand what's exactly happening
there but probably probably going to be
running fairly low as well during some
types of activities the metabolic speed
those what also controls or regulates
fatigue so sometimes during some types
of activity you're simply not performing
well not because you're out of say
glycogen or fat it's just because you
can't create speed fast enough so in the
examples we've used before if we have to
start using energy systems that are
slower it's not that we're out of ATP or
that we're building up too much waste
it's so we're not going fast enough
because we can't get into the right
energy system so that's why I call
metabolic speed we're just not fast
enough right not not getting us there
and then of course we've talked
extensively about how pH is a problem
right so the enzymes the machinery that
you use to create ATP or to even
hydrolyze the split ATP don't function
well in extremely acidic environments so
that'll be a problem there when the
muscle starts getting fatigued it's
gonna start reaching out to the blood
right because the blood is passing right
on by it and it's going to start doing a
whole host of things the job of the
blood is to store the glucose right so
we store glycogen in muscle and in one
other place which we'll get to in a
second we store the glucose in the blood
we also have certainly a lot of fat
we've talked about in previous videos
how when we mobilize fat from our arm or
our stomach or our leg and we want to
put that into our quadriceps for energy
that has to go in the blood right that's
us that's a multiple step system where
we have to metabolize it attach now
human put in blood etc etcetera move it
all the way around okay now so it's
going to have some fat in our blood
the other major job of course the blood
is to bring in oxygen into the cell and
to take carbon dioxide lactate which is
that LH negative and the h plus the
hydrogen proton out so those three items
carbon dioxide hydrogen and lactate we
want out of the cell while we put
carbohydrate glucose fat and oxygen into
the cell so when we globally talked
about this is get nutrients in and waste
products out the nutrients in our the
glucose fat a no 2 and that waste
products out our the co2 by time and
hydrogen another major role in the blood
is this capillary density / blood
distribution so remember the better I am
at getting these products in and out
accordingly the less fatigue happens at
the level of the muscle so when you have
muscular fatigue I don't necessarily
know if it's actually the muscle per se
or if it's a problem getting clearance
so if I'm having a hard time getting
things out of the muscle it may not be
the fault of the mosula may be the fact
that you have low capillary density are
not enough capillaries so you have no
place to where the blood can exchange
into the muscle to get this stuff out so
this could be a capillary issue really
could be a blood flow issue rather than
a natural muscle issue now for I'm a
practical perspective you may not ever
know without taking a biopsy or doing
some imaging my point being we can do
certain types of training that Dr
capillary density and enhance it right
and we'll get into more of this detail
with the capillary density in just a
second but moving on to the blood since
we're here we got to talk a little bit
more detail so if we look at
specifically what's in blood if you were
to go get your blood drawn they would
take it through a center if you spit it
all down it was separate into two major
categories category one is basically
plasma which is 90% water a bunch of
other awesome stuff but for the purposes
of right now we'll just think about as
water and the other component of the red
blood cells and you notice of all that
total blood about 50% of it
red blood cell about 50% of it is water
well the numbers are actually a little
bit different than that and we call that
the hematocrit so keep in mind a major
mistake I hear with from at Comerica all
the time is a matter it is not a number
an absolute number it is a percentage
right so I said it over time ematic rich
is a percentage it's going to come in
handy just a second and certainly in my
class so the percentage of your blood
that is red blood cells is your
hematocrit so in men that tends to be
around 45 46 % and women it's a lot
lower for a whole host of reasons okay
now you can manipulate your hematocrit
but it gets deceiving all right so we
have to break this number down a little
bit what I can tell you is some athletic
agencies have regulations on hematocrit
and so in other words if you're normally
46 percent you show up to a race at 55
percent that is an indication you have
likely blood doped because blood doping
is often taking this exact formula
dumping out the water harvesting a bunch
of those red blood cells waiting for
your body to real rebuild that normal
storage back up and then taking those
extra red blood cells and jamming them
back into your blood now we know red
blood cells carry all of our oxygen so
if I do that my hematocrit goes way up
my performance goes up to an extent but
if I'm normally have 45% and all of a
sudden I'm at 55%
I very especially very quickly within a
matter of weeks or something I'm very
likely have injected red blood cells
back into my own body and so this is a
this has been been gone on a long time
with endurance sports and testing is
very good it's hard to get away with it
now but that's a classic thing that you
would do with blood doping when though
one of the original methods of it
alright well the point being the
madacorp changes with training are a
very common adaptation so the question I
have for you now is would increasing
blood help endurance in other words do
you think with chronic endurance
training and it really doesn't matter if
you're doing the high-intensity stuff or
the long duration stuff probably not
muscular endurance though
if you're doing those types of training
would you have more total blood say
after eight ten twelve weeks of training
would you have more total blood in your
body would you have a higher red blood
cell count would you have a higher
hematocrit so these are questions I
would expect you'd be able to answer
very very confidently so what are they
yes
no not sure well here we go
so not only do you increase total blood
it's probably the single biggest and
most important adaptation to any type of
endurance training is to have more blood
certainly anything from that
high-intensity interval on the long
duration or anything between having more
total blood is huge because it allows
you to carry more red blood cells if I
simply have more red blood cells what my
total blood didn't go up as you can see
depicted here my hematocrit would be
really high but the problem with that
would be my blood would be way too
viscous it would be too thick so in
order for me to be able to handle more
total red blood cells in my blood I have
to match that with an increase in water
so my hematocrit might go up a little
bit or in this example here that
madacorp technically went down a little
bit but if you look at the numbers so in
the pre training example this individual
has five total litres of blood and 2.2
of those leaders are red blood cells so
2.2 divided by five is 44 well after
training they now have 5.8 liters they
put they've added almost a full liter of
additional blood now the hematocrit down
because they added more water than they
did red blood cells but look at the
absolute amount of red blood cells
pre-training there was 2.2 total liters
of blood cells in the body now there are
two point four so he has added point two
liters of actual red blood cells so even
though his matica didn't change
he had more red blood cells and that's
what matters so having more total blood
which allows you to have more total red
blood cells is a critically important
adaptation for Bechet virtually any type
of endurance training so it happens and
this is very very very helpful that
again allows us to carry more blood
sorry more oxygen which means more
oxygen delivery to the tissue and this
is a very very very good thing right so
far to ask you again does red blood or
do the total blood go up yes do does a
total amount of red blood cells go up
yes
does hematocrit go up well it typically
does but you could argue maybe it
doesn't change or goes down a little bit
right but the general answer is yes so
even though this example shows it going
down typically it goes up but even if it
didn't go up it's not the worst thing
ever because to too much red blood cells
in in the the blood without an increase
of water means too thick too thick of
blood pumping through you is kind of
like sludge and it's not very effective
so you really don't want much more than
50 52 percent at the highest standing
waste from there on you just want more
total blood not necessarily just jacking
a more red blood size okay so hopefully
that was clear in terms of capillary
density here's what these things are you
know that what your a or it is in your
veins do right here it is aren't your
arteries in your veins do arteries go
away from the heart typically are
oxygenated but not always veins go back
to the heart typically deoxygenated but
not always there's one particular
example when it goes to the lungs and
stuff that throw that all but the
difference arteries go away veins go
back so the difference between an artery
and a vein is the muscle
in other words arteries go away from the
heart they go to a muscle arteries turn
into capillaries capillaries surround my
soul to shoo they leave the muscle
tissue as a vein and go back to the
heart and the reason we do that is
because you can have one giant artery
going into a muscle we split that up in
a whole bunch of tiny little
distributors surround the muscle now the
reason we do that is enhance our gas
exchange so when I take a single a
venule like that and I split it up in a
whole bunch of thousands of tiny little
ones what happens is a basic pressure
equation it would be like if you had
water going through your hose and all
set at the end
up into a whole bunch of little
tributaries well because there's so much
more area the pressure goes way down so
the flow the blood through the area goes
way down slower blood flow past your
muscle increases the time you have to
get the nutrients in and the waste out
and so blood comes rushing into the
muscle get split up into capillaries
sort of slows down and by the time it
finishes those it goes back together
into a vein the muscle contracts and
shoots it back up out okay and so this
is another reason why enhancing
capillary density dislike that improves
performance right because number one
that allows more places for gas exchange
more complete coverage of all aspects of
the muscle and as well as it slows down
the transit time the amount of time that
it the order of the calf waves go past
the muscle is really really increased so
the time is increased the speed though
is slower same thing right so we have
more gas exchange so it looks like
something like that right so it's read
kind of coming in and the more these
exchange sites I have the more likely it
is to be blue or deoxygenated going out
alright someone who is more fit or
better at this stuff is better at
extracting all of those nutrients on the
way through and they don't leave any
left for waste right but also better
getting the waste products back out so
if we go back to our our list here or a
slide show hopefully you'll understand
that blood aspect a little bit more now
in the previous videos I talked about
what happens when the muscle starts
running low on substrates particularly
carbohydrates in fact it's going to
reach out to the next thing that sub
that holds these or stores these which
is the liver rights to the liver stores
glycogen
so to recap what we said earlier the
muscle and liver store glycogen the
blood source glucose so the muscle
starts exercising it starts running low
on its glycogen it reaches out and
starts stealing glucose from the blood
well that's a problem right because a
blood glucose gets really low blood
sugar and the way to say it you pass out
why and this is a good a cool part why
does that actually happen
well because the brains primary fuel
source is glucose and so the the
endogenous reaction of your body is to
say hey look blood glucose is getting
really low we're gonna have a problem
upstairs I don't care how bad you want
it how a mentally tough you are I'm
taking you down and boom you pass out
you go down it stops you from exercising
because it needs to preserve the brain
the brain it takes a huge chunk of your
basal energy it goes down or stays same
during exercise but the total
expenditure of energy goes up right so
the brain is a real big problem well in
order to snot let that happen the liver
says wait a minute I'm kind of like the
backup system for the muscle glycogen so
the liver is huge right it's right over
here it's really big-ass organ massive
and it stores a ton of glycogen well
relative anyways it stores a ton
relative to the blood not as nearly as
much as muscle and not nearly as much
fat issue store not even close but it
stores a lot then so you start
exercising muscle glycogen gets low you
start taking glucose from the blood
blood sugar starts getting low liver
starts going oh whoa whoa I got you
let me split up some of this glycogen
kick it into the blood is glucose and I
will make sure that while the muscle
keeps burning muscle glycogen and muscle
glycogen levels starts going down blood
glucose stays the same or fact what you
typically see happen during exercise
blood the glucose levels go up well
that's all great
until the glycogen and liver runs out
that's your backup system oops so what
happens when the liver starts running
out of his own glycogen well now we
start seeing the wall we start seeing a
true bomb right when the signals of them
start coming from the liver that says we
are out of glycogen you start having
problems so in our sports nutrition
class I'll certainly talk about those
supplements you can take during exercise
or nutrition during exercise or pre
exercise maybe even a week before to
start combative miss but that's the
basic physiology the other thing you
start doing is reaching out to the
adipose tissue so this is actually what
fat looks like by the way and if you're
doing something where you can use fat as
a fuel source you'll start taking
stored at a fat from the adipocytes of
fat tissue putting that into blood
through the system before he talked
about it length now moving that in and
will start transporting whether it's the
glucose or the fat and bringing that up
into muscles so you can see the arrow
from the blood back into the muscle
tissue there now unlike the liver you're
basically never going to run out of fat
stored fat so even the people who
someone who is 3% body fat still has way
more body fat than they'll really need
for virtually any type of exercise so
there's no limitation there the downside
of course is not that it's going to run
out but it's just too slow
so of course glycogen means much faster
that'll be the problems ok moving on
from that though we kind of have to take
a little sidestep so going back in the
blood we got to talk about what
regulates actually the blood getting
through so we talked about capillaries
and that's going to help us determine
how effective we get what's in the blood
into the muscle but how effective we get
the bullet around the body is actually a
heart issue and so we'll start talking
about the hard a little bit here it's
job is to circulate blood of course and
the two main things we need to be
concerned about our or heart rate of
course how often um bring um pumping and
what's called my stroke volume so the
stroke volume is a appt appropriately
named it is the amount of volume of
blood you kick out per stroke or per
contraction so if I know how much I'm
how often I'm contracting and I know how
I'm kicking out per contraction I can
calculate exactly how much blood I'm
kicking around the by well I know you
know what happens with heart rate with
training and with exercise but stroke
volume may not be as intuitive so let's
take a quick second to review some
cardiovascular physiology ur heart
physiology unless so the intrinsic rate
of the heart is actually a lot higher
than what you think so what you're
looking at on the bottom is heart rate
or beats per minute and what you see is
the actual intrinsic rate so what the
heart would like to be that is actually
close with like 100 120 beats per minute
now hopefully none of you are watching
his video in your heart rates 120 unless
you're just super excited and to which I
would say if your heart rate is this
high watching this damn video you need
to kick in like 500 bucks to patreon
that's ridiculous right you shouldn't be
that excited
okay well your heart doesn't actually
beat there um a normal person is going
to be beating 60 to 80 beats per minute
a decently trained athlete maybe 50
you're really well turned out 3540 right
getting the low end and so what you
actually do is you have a nerve that
drips down on to your heart called the
vagus nerve not the vagus like the the
EGA s it's the VA gu s the vagus nerve
and the vagus nerve activates what's
called the parasympathetic nervous
system okay so if this is actually
slightly opposite because you remember
from skeletal muscle physiology in the
skeletal system if you some if you leak
out if you transmit acetylcholine that
causes them also to contract right well
when you leak out see the choline from
the vagus nerve it actually causes the
heart to slowing it down it inhibits
contraction so the vagus nerves submits
that or releases that acetylcholine that
activates a parasympathetic nervous
system which is your rest and digest
right and that actually slows your heart
rate down and that's why you're sitting
in class for watching this video right
now and you're like 80 beats per minute
you're inquisitive you're not asleep
hopefully I are awake when you're fine
you're not tired there but you're not
also like that right you're not ready to
go at 120 if I want to put you to sleep
or if you're watching this video post
lunch or something like that and you
notice the boy this one's going on right
what's happened is the parasympathetic
nervous system has picked up or
increased its activation and you've gone
from there down to there there right so
obviously you realize your heart rate
goes down when you go to sleep right it
slows way down you get super super tired
now this is something we could take
maybe a separate video but you need to
be able to understand this because
there's lots of tricks you can use with
your athletes or your clients to help
them get into parasympathetic I would
recommend checking out Zell Miller and
yoga tune-up Brian Mackenzie our to
breath a lot of XP tpj nessler a lot of
people have a lot of good trip tricks
and tips about how to get an athlete
parasympathetic and in fact a little
spoiler there is actually really
decent data that shows the faster you
can get into parasympathetic post
workout in some cases the adaptations to
endurance specifically are enhanced so
it's probably not a good idea to do like
a 45-minute blast throw up oh my god I'm
dying so exhausted workout and then go
right back to work you probably need to
submit to spend some time getting
recharge back into parasympathetic
getting turned back down before you then
go back to work or go see your kids or
whatever you have to do but nonetheless
and again another spoiler you can just
simply do this with regulating your
breath but you have to go to those other
sites or maybe I'll make a video about
it let me know yeah I love the health
let me know if you want see video like
that and maybe we'll make one
nonetheless you're down of 3540 you're
cruising you're kind of sleepy well in
order to get back up to eighty you don't
have to add a trendline you don't need
to take caffeine you just simply need to
back off the throttle from the
parasympathetic nervous system so you
take your foot off the brake there a
little bit you go right back to there
you take your foot off the brake even
more and you go up to 120 so here's the
analogy I give imagine you're in a car
going down the hills of San Francisco
the parasympathetic nervous system is
your foot on brake you want to slow down
you push that brake even farther you
want to slow down more you push even
farther open now you want to go a little
bit faster I don't have to hit the gas
pedal I just take my foot off the brake
a little bit gonna go faster I take my
foot completely off the brake
and I'm actually going faster than I
would like to go 120 okay now I'm going
down that hill I'm going as fast as
possible I'm not touching the brake at
all but that's not fast enough I want to
go faster now I can hit the gas a little
bit and the gas is the sympathetic
nervous system so that's how we regulate
our heart rate rise we can go from 120
to up to say 200 depending on you know
all kinds other factors most people have
a max heart rate is somewhere between
165 and 210 215 right I've routinely had
mine 210 215 I know the math trust me
those those estimation equations 220
minus your age they're just random
equations they're not not incredibly
accurate to the
I've had extremely high-level endurance
athletes with a maximum of 170 and I've
been at 210 but I've actually literally
I think the highest I've gotten is 213
and I'm not even close to what I would
call a high-level enters a plea right so
it's really physiologically depends on a
person my point being it's that vagus
nerve that can withdraw its
acetylcholine and or we can hit you with
some adrenaline and we can up regulate
down regulate our basal heart rate so
here's what happens
heart rate goes up we're contracting
more this increases blood flow
throughout our entire system right well
because of that we have an increase in
what's called venous return so this is
the amount of blood coming back into the
heart from the venous system so it
contracted went throughout the body and
it came back up the more I can track the
more I send out the more comes back up
into it right basic pendulum farther I
push it farther it's gonna swing back
the other direction so that increase in
Pheonix return means we have more blood
slamming into the heart on its way back
in now in my class we've talked about
the last couple of sections what happens
when I put an eccentric stretch on a
muscle youie centrically stretch
something in fact especially when you
leave centrically stress something
really quickly stretch sorting cycle
kicks in and simply the elasticity of
the tissue kicks in more appropriately
in this case the elasticity the tissue
and the more you stretch it the faster
you stretch the faster wants to contract
back so by increasing your heart rate
you've increased the blood flow you've
increased the amount of blood smashing
back into the heart that eccentric
stress on the heart increases the
contractility of the left ventricle that
then causes a left ventral ventricle to
contract with more force therefore
enhancing or increasing stroke volume
it's just like your hamstring or your
pack or anything else if I give myself a
big strong eccentric contraction in my
PEC my PEC will respond by contracting
harder and faster it's exactly what your
left ventricle is doing you're slamming
more blood back into it it gets a big
stretch it responds by contracting
harder and faster
in terms of the heart how hard we
contract how much blood we kick out per
squeeze is called our stroke line it's
kind of like the strength metric of your
cardiovascular system or specifically a
heart okay
so as I'm working out and I'm working
actualize I'm really hard my heart rates
going up well I'm also elevating my
stroke volume if I take that stroke
volume how much I squeeze get out per
squeeze multiply that by how many
squeezes I'm getting per minute I get
what's called my Q or my cardiac output
so if both of those things go up my
cardiac output goes up and this is a
huge driver of endurance performance
enhanced cardiac output
it helps acutely and it helps
chronically alright so again we have two
ways to get that our heart rate on our
stroke line now there's not much you can
do about your max heart rate but you can
see significant improvements in your
stroke volume of training so with
chronic training or chronic endurance
training we do seem increasing a left
ventricle size and this is the good
stuff
right this is the this is not a
reduction in chamber size so the
interior chamber where you store the
blood does not go down that's the bad
kind of heart adaptation that's a bad
kind of hypertrophy this is the chamber
stays the same or gets larger but we
thicken up the outside of left ventricle
which means we put more muscle mass on
right we put a bigger glute muscle on
there but we don't shorten down the
muscle or anything like that right I
don't know what that was sorry
little little model kicked my ass out
demonstration but nonetheless then left
ventricle size goes up in a good way
left ventricle strength again the amount
of units of force it can produce goes up
these things combine to increase the
stroke volume and because of that max
heart or sorry heart rate goes down
so to recap when I'm exercising really
hard my heart rate goes up and my stroke
volume goes up because that venous
return that makes cardiac output go up
but at rest you've gotten that chronic
adaptation you've gotten that chronic
hypertrophy and you got that chronic
increase in left ventricular strength so
even resting my stroke volume is
increased
because I'm kicking more out per pump I
don't have to pump as often and so
that's folks what allows what you all
know to be true in that the more trained
you are the lower your resting heart
rate it's generally mostly because you
have more blood because that you have a
greater venous return the increased risk
return helps you build up the strength
inside the left ventricle so you kick
out more blood per pump so you don't
have to bump us off right and that's the
physiology behind why your resting heart
rate goes down with chronic training
again this doesn't really matter if
you're doing high intensity intervals
you're doing long duration stuff I'm not
saying they're identical I'm saying they
both would cause this adaptation
probably not the muscular turn stuff
certainly the anaerobic capacity stuff
the aerobic capacity and long duration
steady-state stuff all of those are
probably going to give you good
adaptation in this area so that being
said I'm basically giving you now the
equation for vo2 max this is the maximum
volume of oxygen you can bring in and
utilize I just haven't been explicit
about so this is what they claim is you
can look it up on your own I've
color-coordinated them for you so vo2
max is really Q which is how much blood
you pump per minute talked about that
multiplied by what's called your AV o2
difference and that's a fancy way of
saying how much oxygen the muscle steals
from the blood so a big arteries veins
mean vesicles it's Oh to difference that
number literally is calculate how much
oxygen is in the arteries fully
oxygenated let's say that numbers can
also number is eight just to make the
math nice you have eight you have eight
oxygen molecules in the artery fully
oxygenated eight it goes by the muscle
the muscle takes on the oxygen right
then we have the vein well how much is
left in vein
so if there's five left in the vein
there was eight going in there's five
left so what's the AV o2 difference 8
minus 5 is 3 so you have extracted 3 of
the auction molecules in the muscle it's
not a very good ratio if I got you
trained and we worked really hard
now when eight went in
now maybe only to come out the vein so
my eight minus two is now six my AV o2
difference increased because I was
better at taking oxygen out of the blood
now you're all so damn smart I know you
see where this is going
how was I able to get better at taking
more option out of blood that's right I
increased the number of capillaries see
how this stuff all works together right
so if I want to improve my vo2 max which
is my ability to bring in and utilize
oxygen it's my maximal aerobic capacity
I need to understand well how much blood
am i bringing in and pumping around the
body and then how good am I taking out
that oxygen in the muscle all right so
you can see the equation at the bottom
there another way to think about this
the cubing cardiac output is simply the
heart rate multiplied by the stroke
flowing which we've already been over
and so this is a classic example of
what's called the Fick equation okay and
what I've shown you at the bottom are
the arrows with what happens with
chronic training so we know without
question vo2 max goes up with training
and a good chunk 20% or more in a year
of training if you can't maybe a couple
years depends where you're at right
obviously the more trained you are the
less improvement you get in terms of
numbers I think it's actually probably
pretty good for you to know most kind of
like untrained college men well be in
the 40s or so for their vo2 max women a
little bit lower 35 a lot of my MMA
fighters are between 55 and 65 typically
closer to the 60 65 but a high level
endurance athlete like a true steady
state endurance athlete they may be 70
75 people have been as high as 90 95
getting close to 100 some of them but
the point is the vo2 max will certainly
go up a training stroke volume at
maximum will go up like we talked about
and so will the a/o food a AV o2
difference now not much but it will go
up because you'll have more of those
capillaries don't get tricked here like
2030 some percent of people with my
classify misses question heart rate
though doesn't go up at a maximum
it's simply determined kind of by rage
so that doesn't go up the time we'll get
into the fatigue of this so why this
happens later but maximum heart rate
doesn't go up maximum a stroke volume up
maximum vo2 max up maximum maybe o2
difference and because of that like I
said our vo2 max goes up i've also
summarized this in a nice chart for you
if you just kind of want to
conceptualize so what I've done is I've
shown you all those variables and what
happens at different things so what
happens at rest what happens at sub max
so what happens at max so hopefully you
can work yourself through a chart like
this and be able to identify what's
going to happen at all three different
areas so if we look at the actual
anatomy of the heart you don't have to
know it in my class but I think it is
important you should understand all the
valves and ventricles and veins and and
what they do well what causes fatigue or
the waste products associated with the
heart number one is it's almost entirely
a slow twitch muscle in fact the slow
touch fibers in the cardiovascular re
are even more slow twitch than those in
your skeletal muscle so it is a
primarily a super slow twitch muscle so
we does not give able to generate any
energy really really fast but the
primary limitation here is the time it
takes to fill the ventricles or the
arteries so when I remember earlier when
I said your max heart rate doesn't go up
a training well that's because it's
limited by your ability to fill the time
so if you are contracting every second
or so there's plenty of time when I'm
not contracting to fill up the ventricle
so I can squeeze blood out but if I'm
attracting I won't do it too so don't
blow your ears out but if I'm
contracting at a super fast rate that
leaves no time to actually fill the
ventricle with blood you have to
remember blood comes in the right artery
goes in a left ventricle squeeze that
left ventricle you go to the lungs comes
back from the lungs with fully
oxygenated goes back into the left
artery goes in the left ventricle left
ventricle squeezes it out and goes all
the way to your blood fully oxygenated
right well if I'm spending so much time
contracting then I'm basically in tetany
and there's no time fat left ventricle
to actually fill up a blood and so that
that pace turns out to be right
onde two hundred or so beats per minute
and that goes down with age and so you
don't really want to exceed that place
because you'd actually lose your stroke
volume because you would actually lose
the amount of blood that gets back into
it so that's not really good thing so in
terms of fatigue at the level of the
actual heart itself it's pretty much
limited by the stroke volume because
it's either weak or small or because we
don't have enough venous return because
we don't have enough blood or because we
don't have enough time to fill okay so
hopefully that section makes a little
bit more sense now now to really round
us out we have to go to our last piece
which is number six and that's the lung
so the boilage at the point in terms of
performance here of the lungs is to
inhale oxygen and exhale carbon dioxide
now go check out the physiology of fat
videos the five and the 55 minute ones
if you want to know exactly what the
heck's going on there in addition
hopefully that co2 piece makes a lot
more sense now that you've been through
the metabolism how we make energy
fifty-five minute videos well alright
you realize the end product of all
metabolism regardless of whether it's
coming for fat carbohydrate or anything
else it all ends up as ATP which we use
for energy water and co2 and then that
all comes out right all of our waste
goes out in our breath but the other
component here the lungs are the
inspiratory muscles themselves so if we
understand how the actual ribs work we
understand those actual eating muscles
to contract as well and those are
susceptible to fatigue so if we look at
the lungs really really quickly I'll
finally get to our question here which
is why you actually breathe well it's to
bring in oxygen yes but the reason you
actually bring in oxygen the only reason
you care about it is because you have to
have that to produce ATP
it's not about oxygen oxygen is not a
fuel it is not a fuel if you think oh
yeah it is because if I tried a lot of
fire and there's no oxygen a fire will
start you're correct it is a requirement
for scalable energy production but if
you're burning something what's the
actual fuel
fire it's the freaking thing you're
burning it's the wood it's the house
it's the paper that's the substrate
that's the fuel it's my fat
it's my carbohydrate it's not the oxygen
I need the oxygen because I have to have
something I can bind to the free carbon
to make co2 remember whether I'm burning
fat or carbohydrate I'm liberating I'm
breaking a carbon bond that gives me
energy to make ATP
but then that carbons floating around
there's an acid problem there there's a
transportation problem so the body won't
do that
biology won't do that chemistry won't do
that unless we've got a free oxygen
that's available to bond to it to make
it a co2 that we can release as energy
so the only damn reason we breathe is so
that we can manage our carbons we can
get rid of those damn things so that we
can make ATP if there was some way that
you can make ATP
samms any oxygen you would never have to
breathe no problem all right so that's
why you actually breathe it's energy
issue not an oxygenation but getting
back to physiology we have intercostal
muscles which of these tiny little
muscles that go in between our ribs then
we've got a diaphragm sits right below
rib cages you can see in the diagram
there well this is a pressure issue so
we know that there's a relationship
between pressure area pressure and area
right so if I increase the area that
decreases pressure right because now all
the things that are packed into this
much area I give this much area things
spread out the opposite happens if I
condense the area too much pressure
happens well the only reason you
exchange gas with your environment is
because of a pressure gradient I know
you've all heard that there's less
oxygen and elevation
that's hot garbage it's not true I don't
care how many times Joe Rogan said it
it's not true there's the exact same in
oxygen at the top of Mount Everest there
is in Las Vegas the difference is the
pressure gradient so when I open my
mouth right now if there's a difference
in pressure between the outside world
and inside of my lungs then things will
move until I equilibrate that pressure
when in terms of your body you have
oxygen and you have co2 in the
environment
same exact thing plus nitrogen well it
turns out in my body it's the exact
opposite ratio of those things as there
is in the environment basically so when
I open up my mouth those two things
exchange example when I open up my own
mouth and I have a lot of co2 in my
blood and I have a little amount of
oxygen and I open my mouth and I expose
it to the environment where there is a
little tiny bit of co2 and a lot of
oxygen oxygen wants to run back into my
mouth and co2 wants to run out okay when
it's the opposite I go and I breathe in
I contract my diaphragm which goes down
I contract my intercostals which opens
up this whole space so what happens the
pressure in my lung cavity it actually
begets a becomes a lot lower than the
pressure in the environment so it's high
pressure outside low pressure inside
airflow goes in well the problem at
elevation is the pressure in the
environment is super low so even though
I get a really low pressure inside of my
thoracic cavity all I'm doing is really
matching it to the external environment
so gas exchange doesn't really happen so
you've got to work really hard to
actively suck in the air when I go below
sea level there's a ton of pressure
super pressure outside so I only have to
make a little adjustment increase the
area of my thoracic cavity a little bit
and an air goes flowing in but once I've
done that all right so the active
process I've used ATP of used
carbohydrate metabolism in my
intercostals for fat metabolism I
contracted that muscle open up the area
well the exhalation is passive right so
I don't have to contract anything I just
have to relax the muscle groups that
smashes the area that creates a lot of
pressure in the thoracic cavity so when
I open up the pressures now higher my
thoracic cavity lower in the environment
so air goes well during exercise the
inhalation is still an active process
but out next exercise I need to get that
carbon dioxide out
faster and so I make the exhalation
process active I start squeezing and
contracting right squeezing and
contracting and trying to put that stuff
together I pulled my diaphragm Palmira
diaphragm down now we don't have the
time to get into it in this video but
this is a huge component to performance
we have shown in our laboratory and many
others actually this is actually
extensive in literature I didn't believe
this at all until I looked into this
evidence base and it's really well
defined you need to train your
intercostal muscles and your diaphragm
and you need to warm them up just like
you would train your hamstrings and you
would train your and warm your
hamstrings up prior to squatting or
sprinting so there's a whole bunch of
ways you can do this I think the best
way that I have seen so far is simply to
practice nasal only breathing so by
shutting your mouth you restrict airflow
that causes the diaphragm and the
intercostals to have to work a little
bit harder to get in air and to get out
waste products so I think there's a
really good way to train yourself so
that's my first recommendation you want
to know more past this you got to dive
into the folks material who experts in
this area but we've shown in our lab
just an acute warm-up all the
intercostal muscles and have a
significant improvement in your vo2 max
for example or anything else training
has a very good carryover to them so
there's a lot of ways you explore this
right so I wanted to bring that up I
wanted to explain in class before we've
gone over the physics of diaphragm ik
breathing versus chest or clavicular
breathing right and if you have my
classic quick answer being we want to
breathe through our diaphragm for these
reasons not through our chest and then
again I've also explained nasal versus
mouth I actually like a lot
what power speed endurance does in terms
of therefore gear system I think it's
magnificent check that out but we should
probably be able and that's where a
professional fighter hugs with a frost
oh we've got about 17 broken noses and
you can't breathe through nose at all
but for the most part we should be able
to do produce some sort of least Basil's
we're walking around in class taking
notes as we're walking the dog
we should be able to function most of
our breathing through our nose right
those pros and cons of both nasal and
mouth breathing but this is some
important stuff that we can actually
play with in class so that being said
this is as I mentioned begin this video
this is an actually a booming area of
research as well as application so I'll
be excited in the next few years to come
back and take a look at some of this
breathing stuff but nonetheless we've
now covered all of the six different
physiological systems that play a role
in endurance or fatigue or condition
performance so what I'd like to do now
is to make sure that you understand each
type of endurance a three that I have
laid out slash forward and all of the
thousands of other ones I haven't talked
about having very specific point of
failure somewhere one two six I'm
totally the beginning this video you
need to understand one through six in
fact most of these things have multiple
places of failure so my challenge to you
going forward think about the type of
training workouts you do think about the
athletes demands and think through all
of these systems and go hey you know
what I bet when I do this type of
workout I'm probably seeing fatigue at
the level of the nerve muscle and maybe
blood but not the last three but this
type of workout really it's all about
lung fatigue and maybe the
cardiovascular system but muscle I'm not
running out of glycogen or the nerves
aren't becoming depleted or getting
excess acid build up earning life so
think through that again I don't want to
teach you the details of every single
type of exercise with the six six six
part system you need I want you to think
through all this stuff so my challenge
to you my homework if you will is to go
through a slide like this or add extras
please at extras think about what you do
in add more and think about okay if I'm
doing like a max power thing or match
strength one rep max max vertical jump
go through each one of those six
individual systems and think where are
they failing and why do the same thing
for say hey max repetitions at 50% of
your one on max squat or bench or death
or winner
one through six where's the failure and
why
if you're in my class this is an actual
homework assignment so the next time we
mean class you need to go through all
four of these endurance examples and you
need to go through all six systems and
talk about where all the possible points
of failure of all six so give you one
here as an example you're lucky
listeners at home I wasn't going to give
you any of this but to make sure my
students understand this assignment
let's go through interval training so
imagine you did 30 on 30 off and we're
going to go through each one of the six
places of failure the six physiological
systems so I'll start you off with
number one this is the nerve well if
you're doing intervals you're going to
run low on carbohydrate in the nerves
you're going to have a hard time with
the sodium potassium pump that will
fatigue and even have pH issues so for
number one for intervals I just said hey
all three of those things we talked
about they're all susceptible to failure
during interval level two which is a
muscle right you're going to run the one
phosphocreatine you're going to run
really low on muscle glycogen your
intervals if you do enough of them
you're gonna have that metabolic speed
issue right now we're trying to create
things fast and you'll have a pH issue
are we gonna run low on fat no no no
right so that's not on my list I went
through the four things that were
applicable to this type of training
number three right now we've moved on
past muscle and we're into blood well
it's the same thing we have the same
problems here with the exception of fat
again one of the things that the blood
can do is transport fat and have the
cell not really applicable here unless
we did like a hundred rounds but if we
did thirty on thirty off for five ten
rounds that's really not a player the
metabolic speed is too fast and so we
are limited by the other things we
talked about which is getting carbon
dioxide out getting lactic acid out
getting oxygen in getting carbohydrates
in we may start to see some depletions
in blood glucose but we're going to may
start to get low if we do enough rounds
it's centered center right do I give you
the short answer here too so it fits on
the slide but in my class again go
through all the points for each six
system and finish it I'm not going to
give you the rest I'm not going to go
through four or five and six
so the homework he'll turn in will go
through one through six four one two
three all four different categories if
you're at home not in my class I still
think you should really do this in fact
I would love you to do this and then
tell me what your answer is and maybe
I'll let you know if I think your run
around I'll give you a hint as you saw
here many of these different types of
training have multiple places of failure
but not all of them have all so one
example on the board here only has two
spots of failure another one has all six
spots of failure right so hopefully you
enjoyed this video this was a long
series this is a lot of work to put
together appreciate the support as
always subscribe below please that helps
me out this project is a viable thing to
do support share please share on
Facebook on Twitter on Instagram
anywhere that you see viable open up
your old MySpace page put it back up
there so Tom can see it already hell
that guy's nameless but get keep helping
to make these things viable the bigger I
can grow this thing the more people can
see it the more people realize they can
use it in their classes whatever they're
going to use it for my students benefit
you would all benefit and we can improve
learning we get improved interaction and
we get this whole thing moving forward
so thanks a lot Cheers